Hey, welcome to my new show, The
Centrifuge, where we go through the
claims made in health podcasts and shows
and spin out the BS from the
sciencebacked information. In this
episode, I'd like to continue going
through a health podcast featuring Dr.
Casey Means, who is an American medical
doctor, entrepreneur, number one New
York Times best-selling author, and a
health educator, as she was on the J.
Shetty podcast. Now, the first episode
released last week, but you do not need
to have actually watched that one to
continue with this one. So, here's what
Dr. Means covers and what we will be
covering. Number one, getting more
involved or advanced health testing for
[snorts] your health. Number two,
doctors are not being taught how to
interpret lab results in a way that will
help you with your health. Number three,
she takes things a step further by
discussing how medicine ignores
particular health markers because
there's no drugs to treat them. And
number four, finally, we'll also discuss
a study on eating and how it massively
reduces the risk of metabolic syndrome,
a cluster of diseases by an extremely
simple hack. Like last time, I'll supply
you with the highlights at the end if
you're short on time or don't know what
to take away from all this. Let's spin
down the BS.
>> Just quickly speaking to function
health, that is like the next level. And
that is if it's something that's
accessible to you, I recommend every
single person in the world do this if
they can cuz it's over 100 biomarkers
like you said for less than $500,
less than the co-pay that you would pay
at the doctor's office for like 10 labs.
And what that will do is actually give
you a hyper granular picture of what's
going on inside your body and your
metabolism. And I mentioned that there
are three hallmarks of bad energy.
There's chronic inflammation, there's
oxy stress, and there's mitochondrial
dysfunction. And the beauty of the
function health tests is that they
actually have tests that will tell you
about each of those. So you can really
know what's going on.
>> Dr. Means is talking about this function
health extensive panel of tests as a
next step from the basic nearly free
test that she discussed in our last
episode. Now I will link that for you if
you're interested. She discusses three
hallmarks of bad energy which is her
term from her somewhat recently
published book. The three hallmarks are
mitochondrial dysfunction, chronic
inflammation and oxidative stress. Now
these are good choices and often
mentioned in the literature. There's
often disagreement and what should be
considered and what shouldn't like in
this review where the researchers
mentioned the hallmarks are integrity of
barriers and containment of local
perturbations
maintenance of homeostasis over time
recycling and turnover integrations and
circuitries
excuse me and rhythmic oscillations and
an array of adequate responses to
stress. homeostatic resilience, hormetic
regulation, and repair and regeneration.
No wonder scientists can't communicate
well with the public. That sounded like
a bunch of nonsense. Now, I can
understand how someone would prefer bad
energy over that mess. Okay, so there's
other reviews focused on aging that do
incorporate mitochondrial dysfunction
and chronic inflammation explicitly, and
they certainly acknowledge oxidative
stress, though they mention several
others as well. So all in all, I like
her list, though it may not be complete
for the top researchers in the field.
Okay, so good choices, but then the
claim turned to functional health, the
company that she and Mr. Shetty are
investors and test directly for all
three of these problems. So I decided to
look for myself. They have an extensive
panel of inflammation measures like high
sensitivity C reactive protein and
multiple measures of immune cells. So
they definitely test for chronic
inflammation, one of these hallmarks.
However, there are no specific tests for
mitochondrial dysfunction. Now I would
know as I was involved in mitochondrial
research for 10 years and there are also
no direct tests for oxidative stress. In
fact, most if not all of the chronic
inflammation measures are actually found
on basic blood tests. So, if the idea is
to pay a lot of money for these
specialty tests focused on these three
hallmarks,
I would save my money. To give
functional health credit, uh they do
have some additional tests that are less
common like measuring omega6 and omega-3
fat levels, lead and mercury testing and
more. So, if that is the reason that you
use functional health, it may be worth
it. Just not for these three hallmarks
discussed. The takeaway here is that if
you're looking to measure your oxidative
stress, your mitochondrial dysfunction,
or your chronic inflammation, you'd be
better served by using a routine blood
test rather than the functional health
testing. It's much cheaper and just as
effective. But I think I think something
that's again hopefully empowering and
not too scary is that at the best
hospitals and medical schools in America
like Stanford where I went to medical
school, doctors are not learning how to
interpret lab tests in a way that will
help you be empowered to live a
healthier life. We are only learning a
very algorithmic way of looking at lab
markers in isolation in order to
prescribe medications. If LDL is high,
prescribe a statin. If glucose is high,
prescribe metformin
and so on and so forth.
>> So, the claim being that doctors are not
taught in medical school how to analyze
health tests in a way that will help you
have a healthier life. Now, I was
actually debating covering this one
simply because I'm not a clinician. So,
the diagnostic side of things is
slightly outside of my education as a
PhD in medicine, but I'll say that it
does seem true that physicians are
trained to look at irregular blood
values and make quick determinations
based on those blood values. Now, I
feel, and that's a key word there, feel,
not evidenced,
that most doctors likely look at the
context that they have in front of them,
too. I can only speak from my
experience, but each physician that I've
had has looked at my blood work and
applied context to it. Case in point, I
just went a few weeks ago for my routine
physical, and I brought my blood work
from my previous test so we'd have
something to discuss on that blood work.
And on all my blood work, my creatinine
is always high. Now, I know why, and
it's not a concern to me since I've done
the research explained here. But my
physician looked at me and said, "You're
a muscular guy. You work out and you
take creatine. I'm not concerned about
this high creatinine, but I'll do
another test just to be sure." And we
did another test, and sure enough, all
good. I've had this experience with two
or three independent physicians. So, is
that proof? No. But it does speak to the
idea that physicians aren't all brain
dead in looking at blood work like a
robot. There's definitely an algorithmic
style to some of it like heart disease
prevention using a risk estimate
calculation. So, Dr. Means is right to
to that to some degree, but my take is
that it's more nuanced and especially
with a great physician.
Okay. So, I hesitate here because I'm
presenting an argument mostly based on
anecdote, which is not my style. So, if
you want to disregard everything that I
just said, I think that's fair. However,
what is claimed next is far more
scienceheavy and in the same train of
thought.
>> And what's really interesting is that
for the biomarkers that we do not have a
good drug for, we ignore them. like
triglycerides. You rarely hear about
triglycerides, even though they are more
associated with heart disease than LDL.
We only hear about LDL because we have a
medication for it. If uric acid is high,
here's alopurinol. So, we focus on the
biomarkers that have a drug for them.
And what they don't learn is how to look
at the labs in concert with each other
to read the tea leaves of what the labs
are saying together to tell you about
your core physiology.
>> All right. This one struck me because I
was actually curious if something like
blood triglycerides do track better with
cardiovascular disease than something
like LDL. Triglycerides are a particular
type of packaged fat molecule and LDL is
the carrier particle that contains
triglycerides and cholesterol. Generally
up to now to Dr. Mean's point medicine
has focused on lowering LDL
concentration in the blood to help
prevent plaque buildup in our arteries.
So it's atherosclerosis as these LDL
particles are the prime suspect for the
buildup in our plaque in the arteries in
the first place. So is it then true that
triglycerides track more strongly with
heart disease than LDL cholesterol?
Well, the answer is not as clear-cut as
Dr. Means makes it out to be. For
example, without much effort, I found
two studies that showed the opposite. So
triglycerides either did not associate
or did not associate as strongly with
cardiovascular disease as LDL
cholesterol. Still, that doesn't mean
that she's wrong, as there's also
studies that do indicate a stronger
relationship with triglycerides. You can
tell that the confident explanation may
need to be adjusted to a little bit more
nuanced one, though there may be
something to the point itself. However,
addressing this from a different angle,
is it true that there are no medications
for triglycerides? No. We have multiple
from phenopibrate, pumaf fibrate, and
others, including trials using omega-3
fats that people go on about. In fact,
while statins are often prescribed, and
I know some people feel strongly against
those, there are studies comparing
against statins using these triglyceride
reducing drugs like here where the
triglycerides are measured. And we can
see in red that the triglyceride drug
reduced triglycerides substantially
compared to the placebo which was given
a statin alone. Also using an example
like metformin earlier is a bit comical
considering that the price of metformin
is as low as just a few dollars per
month. So it would be in the best
interest of the pharmaceutical companies
to focus on lowering triglycerides as
much as they could because they make way
more money. if only they'd been able to
show that it was actually effective,
which they failed to do in most
circumstances. The key points here are
that lowering triglycerides is a good
thing to do, but it probably shouldn't
come at the expense of reducing one's
LDL cholesterol. And doctors aren't
ignoring triglycerides because there's
no drug to reduce them. They reduce the
emphasis simply because the evidence
isn't as strong. One of the big ones
that I've struggled with for a very long
time because I remember feeling like I
had to do this quick and fast forever.
You talk about eating slowly, which I
think sounds like the easiest, simplest,
but underestimated habit. So, could you
walk us through that?
>> It's incredible. This is also my biggest
challenge as well. So hard,
>> especially as a surgeon, like I just
would wolf food down. And research
strongly shows that the people who eat
the slowest have a four times less
likelihood of developing metabolic
syndrome than people who eat the
fastest. So literally this has nothing
to do with what you're eating. It's how
you're eating. So this should be very
empowering for people cuz it's like even
if you don't want to change the actual
food, change the speed at which you're
eating. And that does change everything.
The average American family is eating
fewer than three meals per week at a
table with the family. Like this is this
has become so normal now that we don't
eat with other people. We eat in our
cars. We eat while we're walking. We eat
on the go. And I think [snorts] just the
key message here is that the more you
can invest in sitting down at a table
and eating slowly and mindfully, it's
literally going to have a profound
impact on your core metabolic health.
>> I think this message is a really good
one emotionally speaking. Now, I
absolutely identify with the idea of
eating around others and slowing down.
It's tough to do sometimes, especially
as I I sometimes prefer to be a hermit,
but it has benefits outside of the
obvious physical health. That said, what
about this study? What about the
physical health benefits? Well, I
actually found several studies looking
into this hack, and I thought it was
quite illuminating, but not necessarily
in the best way. Now, before I touch on
that, if you're interested in a deeper
dive on the relationship between
triglycerides and LDL on why oxidative
stress and mitochondrial dysfunction
being separate may not make any sense,
as well as a specific test for these
hallmarks, a closer look at the
triglycerides relationship to
cardiovascular disease and even more,
then check out the extended version of
this episode. It comes with an article
covering the main points, too. Plus, you
get all these benefits right here as a
member of the Physionic Insiders, my own
research platform and community that
allows me to continue doing this kind of
work for you. The link to check it out
is in the description box. I hope to see
you there. Admittedly, I have no idea
which specific study Dr. Means is
referring, but that's not on her. It's
just the nature of most podcasts. Still,
it doesn't mean that we can't find
useful information on the topic, like
this meta analysis that grouped 29
studies together to identify if there
was a relationship between eating speed
and a few different blood tests like
triglycerides. Now, ultimately, they
indicated that fast eating was related
to increased risk of metabolic syndrome.
Still, for reasons that I won't get into
too much into boring depth, this study
was pretty poor quality. So, I turned my
gaze to another that addressed many of
the concerns that I had. This study
confirmed that eating slower is linked
to reduce risk of particular health
issues like high cholesterol and
triglycerides. Now, interestingly, that
wasn't universally true, like having no
link to type 2 diabetes or high blood
pressure. Still, regardless of the
specifics, which likely need to be
hashed out, it seems that Dr. Means is
correct. There's plenty of data that
point in that direction, though. there's
some holes that would be nice to fill in
the literature. I don't think that the
difference is four times and I looked
for studies that were in that realm.
Many studies indicate benefit of slow
slowing down eating, but none had that
strong of a relationship. The key
takeaway though is slow down. Just slow
down eating. There may be some health
benefits in it for you. So, as usual,
that was a lot, but we did cover a
number of claims. So, where does that
land us applicably and scientifically
speaking? Well, first, while Dr. Means
may push for more extensive lab testing
through a company like Functional Health
to measure oxidative stress,
mitochondrial dysfunction, and chronic
inflammation, after reviewing what they
test, I'm inclined to disagree. You
would be better off saving your money
and getting a routine blood test. That
assumes you only care about those three
hallmarks of health. You could check
your C reactive protein or CRP as well
as your immune cell count. That will
give you some indication of your chronic
inflammation. The other two hallmarks
are not assessed directly by routine
blood tests nor by advanced testing by
functional health. The second thing is
while trying to reduce your blood
triglycerides is a good thing to do if
they're elevated, the research is not as
clear-cut on the benefits in relation to
cardiovascular health. There's some
evidence, but it's much more nuanced
than uh what was led on. I would opt for
a focus on both. So LDL cholesterol and
triglycerides. If both are in the normal
ranges, you're likely in good shape. If
one is elevated, especially LDL
cholesterol, don't ignore it. Third,
there's enough evidence to indicate, as
Dr. Means pointed out, that slowing your
eating time can have an effect at
certain health metrics. So instead of
inhaling your food, if you can, try to
take a bit of time around it, make it an
event. If you're looking for more
analysis, more centrifugation, more
separation of reality from hype, then
check out the episode on going over five
simple, basically free blood tests as
explained by Dr. Means right here.
Otherwise, I'm not really done with the
J Shetty podcast. The next episode
releases right here next week. I
appreciate you sticking it out with me.
Thanks for tuning in and I'll see you in
the next one.